[Music]
this program is brought to you by
stanford university
all right
somebody asked me some questions which i
thought were good questions so i asked
them to write them down and list them
one and i thought i would answer them in
class because other people might be
interested one does the apparent
wavelength of the cosmic radiation
depend on the motion of the observer
i.e is there a doppler effect
if so doesn't that mean there is a
preferred frame the one in which the
wavelength is the same in all directions
neglecting the small
yeah neglecting the small fluctuations
all right so the question is
it's a good question it's a it's a right
question and the answer is yes to almost
all parts of it except where
the author of the question
realized that the answer must be no
all right so
there's a lot of matter around
and also photons all over the place
and
the photons are
isotropic
what does that mean
uh the typical energy of a photon coming
from the left is more or less the same
as not more or less is about the same as
the typical energy of a photon coming
from the right
the temperature
of the photons is pretty well described
by the average energy of the photons and
so if we're way way out in outer space
intergalactic space
and
i'm not talking about the photons that
come from the sun
or from stars i'm talking about the
cosmic microwave background
that which is there
when everything else is removed so to
speak
those photons
appear to be isotropic they come at you
from every direction with about the same
energy but then that means something a
little puzzling not too puzzling but a
little bit puzzling
if
you are moving
through this
mess of stuff including photons mainly
photons
and you were moving through it let's say
to the right with a large velocity large
means comparable to the speed of light
or some fraction of the speed of light
then because of the doppler effect
you would see the photons coming from
this direction as having shorter
wavelength meaning somewhat bluer
than the photons coming from the other
direction
yes some were bluer
meaning to say
that you would have a
bias in directions in the sky
where in some directions
you would see
hotter photons higher energy photons in
other directions you would see lower
energy photons
yes this is true
that is really the way it works
we are moving through the microwave
background our planet uh
moving uh
with a solar system rotation with the
galactic rotation and with the motion of
uh
of the galaxy and the clusters of
galaxies and in fact when we look at the
microwave temperature in different
directions it is not the same in all
directions
one direction is preferred i couldn't
tell you which it is offhand
i mean you know i don't remember but it
is got to do with known motions of the
earth
and so the answer is yes there is such a
doppler effect and yes
there is a preferred frame of reference
the preferred frame of reference is the
one
where the microwave background looks
isotropic from all directions
it happens to be and this is the key
point
it is the same preferred frame of
reference as defined by the galaxies
themselves on the average
the galaxies are at rest in one at any
particular place any particular place
the local galaxies are on the average at
rest in some frame of reference that's a
preferred frame of reference
and it's the same preferred frame of
reference
that the cosmic microwave background is
isotropic
so that's the answer to question number
one
uh
yes there is a special frame of
reference
if not that's even harder to understand
yeah
fortunately we don't have to get into
that part of the question
um
next question
is there anything in relativity to limit
the relative velocity or can two
coordinate points let's just call them
galaxies
can two galaxies have a relative
velocity greater than c greater than the
speed of light
the answer is yes if they're far enough
apart
this is just the hubble law and the
hubble law holds on distances which are
much
which may be arbitrarily large we don't
know for sure
but there's nothing wrong with extending
the hubble law out to distances
such that
velocity is equal to hubble times
distance
if space is as flat as it appears to be
and it does appear to be flat
then there's no obvious bound certainly
nothing within
within observation
no obvious bound on distances
if distance is big as big enough
then
the velocity the relative velocity of us
relativism to some distant galaxy will
exceed the speed of light
can't do anything about it it's true
einstein never said that that was
impossible
let's put it this way what he would say
was impossible
is for one thing to pass another
right in front of your nose at faster
than the speed of light it doesn't say
anything about very distant things
moving relative to each other greater
than the speed of light
but of course if something is moving
faster than the speed of light away from
you and assuming that it continues to do
that then it can never send a message to
you
because
uh if it's
moving away from you with faster than
the speed of light
then
light rays which are sent to the left
and right ways light waves which are
sent to the right will be both swept
along with the motion
and effectively be moving away from you
so
there is no such cosmic limitation on
whether distant things can be moving
away from you
the place where they're moving with the
speed of light relative to you is a
horizon
yeah
wouldn't the light ray set in the
reverse direction the backward
right guard wouldn't that still be
traveling at sea towards you but
stretched in wavelength to where it
is no longer light
it's actually moving away from here
well let's put it this way let's put it
to say let's put it this way
okay the light ray is moving that way
but space is growing faster than the
light ray can can overcome
okay
so
there's a model for this which i like
it's a model which i invented in order
to explain inflation
but uh let's uh so let me explain what
the model is
imagine you have a line
and now you start stretching the line
the line is made up out of atoms okay
the line is made up out of atoms
and now you start stretching it what
happens
eventually it'll break because the
distance between the atoms will grow
larger than the atomic forces can can
handle
but we also have
secretly a source of extra atoms
and every time two atoms gets further
apart than a certain distance we put
another one in
everywhere is that it happens everywhere
as that happens we keep filling it up
with more and more atoms
so that the line
so that the line continues to grow
constantly being resupplied with atoms
okay now it's not atoms really that we
want to think about but it's a good
model for it
then
this line will grow first of all
according to hubble's law
it will also grow exponentially the
distance between any two points will
grow exponentially
and there will be some distance beyond
which
two things will be receding with greater
than the speed of light
but if you go to those places
you can ask supposing here's where the
velocity of separation gets to be about
the speed of light
if you go to the left and you send the
light beam you can still certainly send
the light beam this way and you can send
a light beam that way
the only problem
is the atoms are filling in so fast
that the distance between you
and where the light ray has gotten to
is growing faster than the light ray can
uh
overcome
ask your question
does the
ordinary does the relativistic
formula for the addition of velocities
hold
in other words if we have two observers
three observers and they all pass each
other one after another after another
but it doesn't hold in the case of
velocities
yeah that's right you have to you have
to go back to the first principles again
yeah
there you have to use some uh some more
fancy geometric
if you have two photons that are
radiated from a point their separation
velocity is 2c
yes
so as seen by you as human rights
yeah but you could send something out
with three quarters of the speed of
light that way
and three quarters of the speed of light
the other way
and their relative separation
to you will seem to be one and a half
times the speed of light
but to one of them looking at the other
uh-uh it looks less than the speed of
light this is different
and a photon itself
doesn't have an inertial reference
well moving with the speed of light
so you know the point is you can't
answer questions like this just using
ordinary special relativity you have to
use general
relativity and general relativity allows
the metric of space to expand
when the metric of space is expanding
that's very much like this picture where
molecules
are filling in the gaps in between
for example if this were a ordinary line
of atoms there would be a maximum
velocity on it
what would that maximum an ordinary
maximum velocity the speed of sound on
the uh or the speed of uh waves which
vibrate on the uh
on the string here
we could take it to be the speed of
sound
ordinary
ordinary signals sent back and forth by
elastic vibrations or sound waves and so
forth also have a limiting velocity
as long as you're not
stretching the string and filling it in
and filling it in
then
no
signal
other other than a supersonic signal
no signal which is restricted to be
moving slower than the speed of sound
for some reason
[Music]
no signal which is moving slower than
the speed of sound can exceed the speed
of sound
that's a true statement but now
but now imagine this thing is being
filled in in the way that i described
what is the rule the rule is that the
sound waves relative to the local
molecules
can't exceed the speed of sound
that's going to be our rule right the
sound waves themselves propagating from
one molecule to the next moves through
this material
with a speed of sound and let's also
suppose that nothing else can move
faster
nevertheless if the string is big enough
and long enough
distant parts of it will be moving away
fast enough that they'll be moving away
faster from you just because more and
more is filling in it's filling in so
fast and so much of it is filling in
that a point sufficiently far away
will be moving away
in a way that sound cannot get back to
this point it tries to get back to that
point
it moves in this direction
but by the time it's moved one meter in
this direction
more than a meter's worth of uh of new
molecules have been inserted
all right so general relativity which
allows space to behave in this way
does allow objects
to exceed the speed of sound or speed of
light excuse me in this sense
but not relative to the local
observers
so no observer over here can see a sound
wave going past him
with faster than the speed of sound
are you saying
that recession is a kind of drag
is what it is
the stretching of the wavelengths due to
the expansion
is that due solely to
expansion or is there another element to
it yes
it's totally due to the expansion but
it's not distinct from the doppler
effect it's the same effect
you can solely think of it if you want a
simple way to think about it just think
about it
as being due to the expansion
so a wave on here
when
the
system expands the wave expands with it
that's the simplest way to think about
it
no it's a theoretical statement based on
the general theory of relativity
combined with a theory of waves
propagating in a
in an expanding space
no it is part of
of the mathematics of the general theory
of relativity of expanding space time
if you write a wave equation
in
a geometry which is expanding you will
find the waves expand so it's it's not a
is it an empirical fact
well
yes but not in the sense that we can
actually expand space and uh and see the
wavelength expanding
uh it's an empirical fact an
astronomical fact
but it's also a deeply theoretical fact
that uh that would be very very
surprising if it were false
um this idea came to an idea that adam
is still in the blanks
is that what's really happening out in
the cosmos no it's not atoms
little bits of space little bits of
newly formed space
that's one way to think about it the
other way to think about it is just
through the equations of general
relativity
in which
there is an expanding metric
this is the expansion factor the scale
factor
and the expansion of the scale factor
just produces more and more space
if you like
a model for it people like models
[Music]
is it like expanding a rubber band
no
because rubber bands have this habit of
thinning out when you stretch them
and
let's forget whether they break
somebody living in that rubber band
would notice the fact that with time
the interaction between neighboring
atoms changes
you would notice with time the
properties of the space that he lives in
changing
okay that's not the way
general relativity works it works more
like
the situation where there's a hidden
reservoir of points that you can keep
inserting
so that as time goes on the properties
that one ascribes to a region of space
don't change
the space doesn't thin out in that sense
that's the way the mathematics works
this actually would be very very useful
exactly these equations
would be rather useful
in describing a um
a line of atoms if you really did insert
more more and more atoms they would be
described by by those equations anyway
next let's see did we finish the
questions
yeah
okay
alice and bob from the first lecture is
there a relationship between the
relative velocity exceeding c and the
surface of last scattering and the size
of the observable universe
in other words coming back to this
question
of
here i suppose it's bob
alice is moving outward
well
according to the hubble law
there is some distance out there
is bob
there's some distance out there where
things are just moving away from him
faster than the speed of light
and he can't get signals from them
alice
let's let's let me get the question
again
is there a relationship between the
relative velocity exceeding c
and
and the surface of last scattering yeah
so there's some distance
when alice is beyond that distance her
light waves cannot get back to bob okay
that's called the horizon okay that's
called the horizon
we're going to have more to do with the
horizon but that's just called the
cosmic horizon
and if space is expanding in the right
way
then that cosmic horizon has a fixed
size and it just sits there and bob is
surrounded by it and anything out beyond
that horizon is just invisible to him
because the light can't get back
now
that distance
is the place where the hubble law
says
that distance d
is the place where the hubble law says
that the velocity of recession becomes
equal to the speed of light
it is not quite
the place where the surface of last
scattering is
the surface of last scattering is
slightly in
slightly in it is the place
where if a light ray was emitted from
that place by the time it got to us
its wavelength would have been
infinitely stretched
that's what the horizon is any light ray
emitted from the horizon
by the time it would get to us
why would it why would it be infinitely
stretched
well the reason is fairly simple
a light ray
emitted from very close to that point
takes a very very long time
to get to us
if it takes a long time
then the amount of stretching that
undergoes is enormous but the other way
to think about it is doppler shift
anything that's moving away from us with
close to the speed of light
will emit
doppler shifted radiation that we'll see
stretched
so things coming from the horizon that's
the place where things are infinitely
stretched
uh that is what the horizon is
the horizon is not quite
the surface of last scattering how do we
know that
well the light from the surface of last
scattering we see it it is not
infinitely we don't see it with our
eyeballs we see it with infrared
detectors it's not infinitely red
shifted
in fact it's red shifted by about a
factor of a thousand
it's a thousand times longer wavelength
by the time that it gets to us we
discuss this
than it was when it was emitted
a thousand is a big number to the extent
that a thousand is a big number
the surface of last scattering is very
close to the horizon
where the redshift factor would be
infinite
so for many practical purposes
the surface of last scattering is at the
horizon or close enough to it
yes that does define the size of the
observable universe that's exactly what
the observable universe is
it's a portion of the universe
that light can reach us from
so it's the portion of the universe
within our
cosmic
horizon yeah
but um in in a box let's say there's a
there's a longest wavelength that can
happen
you know i think about
half the distance
uh could you extend that to the universe
no you see not not really
um
here imagine this again
there's nothing
to prepare for forbid you from having an
arbitrarily long wave embedded in this
thing here
that's even larger than the horizon
uh
it's not like being in a box
not quite like being in a box
so a little bit different
okay let's see is there any last
question
yes that's right
distant galaxies
will someday pass beyond the horizon
and will
not only distant galaxies even
relatively close galaxies were passed
behind the horizon
that was my question the d in that since
h is going to be a function of time is d
getting uh shorter oh okay
we'll come to that
h
i said h in principle can be a function
of time and it is a function of time
what we know about the universe today
if it continues the way it's going
is h is asymptotically going to a
constant
so at late times you can think of h as a
constant that's the accelerated
expansion which we're going to come to
today
h is tending toward a constant
that's right so so
uh
once h becomes a constant then this
becomes a relationship between uh
between distances does that mean that we
won't be able to see the microwave
radiation eventually the microwave
radiation will get
will get um stretched and stretched and
stretched and stretched exponentially
and so
it'll just fade out of the existence
that's going to fade out of existence
before nearby galaxies
yeah
well a nearby galaxy will
disappear
with fade out of
um
depends on how good your detectors are
obviously
i will uh yeah i would guess it will
become undetectable before the galaxies
uh uh
right
the microwave
radiation is coming from even more
remote things
than nearby galaxies so if we're not
going to be able to see them
oh by the time the galaxies but yeah
yeah i think that's right
yeah
right
so everything will cool down everything
will disappear behind the horizon
only the things which are accidentally
more or less gravitationally bound to us
the solar system won't fly apart
the galaxy won't fly apart
but the distant galaxies will all recede
and will eventually be left in a as a
truly isolated island with uh nothing to
tell us that those other galaxies are
out there
except history except history books
all right look i want to get on to um
i want to get on to some more
things about cosmology
now the name
we're going to get just a little bit
technical today not too technical
but there are pieces which
are essential
the name of this series of courses at
least in my own mind
are the theoretical minimum
the minimum number of things you need to
know
in order to really understand the next
step
and the next step would mean
following a serious cosmology argument
so i don't skimp on the essentials when
the essentials are hard i do them in the
simplest cleanest
least technical least mathematical way
that i can
but
i try to do them preserving the
essentials we're going to do that today
the other thing i don't like very much
is lots of jargon
but sometimes it's useful to tell you
about the jargon so that when you read
about
astrophysicists determining that w is
equal to -1
you may want to know what w is
and in order to tell you what w is i
will have to tell you what the
definition of w is but there are six
things which are all pretty much the
same with different letters that are
just describe them
so i've sort of
somebody will put this on the on the web
and it's got some definitions and so
forth all right but enough excuses let's
get down to it
what i want to talk about is the
relationship between pressure and energy
no let's go back a step
we're late we're late i'm going to start
the class now we're going to stay a
little bit late today because i want to
deal with some issues here
let me just do a very brief review
so far we have found two kinds of matter
which can cause the universe to expand
one of them was radiation and the other
was just ordinary
atoms sitting still
moving together with the galaxies in
fact they are just the galaxies
one i think i named matter a
matter-dominated universe a universe
which is dominated whose energy is
dominated
by things which are more or less
standing still in their own reference
frame
even though the entire universe is
expanding
as we move along with the expansion
things standing still
massive objects their energy is simply
their mass
and
a universe based on that kind of energy
density is called matter dominated
there's an energy density
let me just write the fundamental
equation over here
the fundamental equation that we
that we've been working with
is that the scale factor
squared square the ratio of the square
this is the hubble constant squared
that's equal
incidentally can green be seen well
does that work
it's not as good as black
let me try black
the trouble is the black ones have
always run out of ink
a dot over a squared that's the hubble
constant squared is equal
to 8 pi
g over 3
times the energy density
as always the speed of light i'll set
equal to 1. 8 pi g over 3 times the
energy density
and that's our basic equation for how
the universe expands a is simply
the scale factor
expands or contracts or whatever it does
alright the energy on the right hand
side can come from various components
and in standard cosmology what's called
the standard model of cosmology
there are basically three components
to the energy density on the right hand
side
the first is matter now matter is by
definition
particles or objects it could be black
holes it could be galaxies but objects
that are at rest moving and at rest
means moving with the overall expansion
that's called matter
such things and the universe that uh
that is matter dominated let's write
down what it means it first of all means
that the energy density
goes like some constant
divided by
this cube of the scale factor
the cube of the scale factor is just the
volume
and if the number of particles within
the volume stays fixed and the mass of
each particle stays fixed
then the energy density
is just the mass within that region i
guess i called it m at one point the
mass within the region divided by the
volume of a co-moving
piece of space
and that's just a cubed so this is
matter dominated
and we solved the equation
[Music]
with that particular
setup and what did we find we find that
the scale factor grew
like t to the two thirds
next we introduced another kind of
energy density
radiation made up out of photons
because the energy of a photon
decreases
when a volume grows imagine a box
imagine expanding the box
each photons wavelength grows its energy
decreases
and so as a increases this is let's call
this matter row matter
rho let's call it radiation
energy density and radiation
instead of being one over a cubed is
some constant divided by a to the fourth
power
it's the fourth power because each
photon
has an energy
which decreases as a gets bigger as one
power of a
this is radiate the radiation dominant
if all there is
is radiation and no other kind of energy
in the universe
then it's called radiation dominated
of course you can have both together
then the equations get more complicated
but in that circumstance a grows like t
to the one half
now the smaller a is
the
the bigger
the radiation component is relative to
the matter component
the smaller a when a is very small this
is bigger than this
so that means in the very early universe
the universe was radiation dominated
after a time
the individual photons lost their
potency because they expanded and the
universe became matter dominated
and so it made a kind of transition not
a sudden transition a smooth transition
from an expansion
like square root of t
to an expansion that was t to the two
thirds this is a little bit faster
expansion than this
uh and that happened after about ten
thousand years pretty early
at least according to the parameters as
we now know them we actually can't see
back to that point but we can infer it
uh by a variety of arguments
all right there is a third component of
energy
that's important in the universe of
course there's zillions of components
but
the important
dynamically important components that
really govern
the way the universe behaves on a large
scale
is
what i'll call rho naught
and that's vacuum energy dark energy
cosmological constant all the same thing
and we're going to come to that tonight
uh what i will tell you about it
is it doesn't depend on a at all
it's energy that's there in the vacuum
think again
about
this growing chain of atoms
waves along here
sound waves
would get less and less energy as the uh
as they got longer and longer wavelength
so they in fact would
would
the energy density would decrease
with time from a sound wave
let's suppose that they were embedded in
this string a set of
impurities
these impurities we do not have a source
of new impurities
we don't have in our pocket a source of
these new impurities let's give those
impurities names let's call them
hydrogen
okay they're hydrogen or we could call
them galaxies or just ordinary stuff
right what happens
as more and more points fill in here
points of space fill in
the
atoms get further and further apart
and so again the energy density
decreases but there is also just the
energy density
i shouldn't have called them atoms i
wanted to reserve atoms for the little
rubber molecules or in here
that we're adding into it these are
galaxies
galaxies galaxies
the galaxies get thinned out by
expansion and so their energy decreases
that's why it decreases here
the sound waves
the number of
waves that can fit in
the wavelengths get longer and longer
the sound waves get less and less potent
less and less energetic
so radiation
which is the analog of the sound waves
also the energy density decreases as a
gets bigger and bigger
but we can just imagine that there's
some kind of energy associated
with the material that the string is
made up out of
it doesn't change with time
it doesn't
it doesn't dilute it doesn't dilute
because every time it tries to dilute we
put another atom in there
the atoms themselves the rubber out
let's call them rubber atoms make
believe the string is made of rubber
uh
every time the distance between rubber
molecules increases we throw another
rubber molecule in there so what happens
to this component of the energy the the
component
that is associated
with the rubber molecules that we put in
that does not go away
as the universe gets bigger and bigger
it stays constant
what's going on locally within that
rubber string
never changes with time and so this
so-called vacuum energy
or dark energy
it's the component which does not
go to zero as a gets bigger it's just a
constant
in fact you can think of it as a
constant of nature it's a number it's
there it's there in the vacuum
it's peculiar you may find it hard i'm
just going to write rho naught equals
rho naught it doesn't change
those are the three components of energy
which are important
in
the evolution of the universe we're
going to talk about them individually
individually now now um
with each component of energy
these are the energy densities of course
these are the energies per unit volume
with each component of energy there is
also a pressure that's associated with
it
let me begin i want to describe how
energy is connected with pressure
pressure is important
in cosmology
so let's talk about the relationship
between
pressure and energy density
particularly let's start with radiation
let's start with radiation
i'm going to start with a one
dimensional box so one dimensional box
is just a line segment
let's imagine that it's actually a
finite line segment for the time being
it's not growing
but it contains photons going back and
forth and the photons move with the
speed of light
every photon has an energy
and when the photons bounce off let's
assume that they bounce off the walls of
the box the walls of the box are just
the ends of the interval what happens
when a photon bounces off
the end of the when it bounces off the
interval
it creates a pressure
it creates a pressure creates radiation
pressure
light bouncing back and forth between
mirrors exerts a pressure on the mirrors
it's that radiation pressure which i
want to uh and the relationship between
the radiation pressure and the energy
density in there that's going to occupy
us for a while
so let's see if we can figure it out
um
the formula let's what we're interested
in now is the force
on the wall of the box
the average the time averaged force
on the wall of the box due to the photon
bouncing back and forth for the moment
just one photon
later on we'll fill it up with lots of
photons
all right
what is the equation for force
force is equal to
the time rate of change of something
what is it the time rate of change of
momentum
p
why does the momentum of a photon change
the momentum of a photon changes because
the photon is originally going to the
right and it changes to the left
supposing let's call a small p small p
stands for momentum
large p will stand for pressure later
pressure and force in one dimension are
the same thing
all right so
um
let's think of the of the photon
rattling back and forth many times
each time it hits the wall
what's the change in the momentum of the
photon
if the photon happens to have a momentum
p
2p
okay so if the magnitude of the momentum
is p when it reflects
there's a change in momentum
twice p
what's the time interval between
successive jolts at the end of the box
here
the photon moves with the speed of light
and the distance is l
so how long does it take between
collisions with a wall
2l over c y2
y2 because it's got to go and come back
all right so the rate at which momentum
is being if you like which momentum is
being deposited on the
wall or the time the momentum per unit
time
[Music]
that's changing by virtue of the
reflection
is twice p
but it happens every what did we say l
over c
2 l over c
all right the twos cancel
and we can write this in the form
pc divided by l
that's the force on
on the wall of the box
now next question
what is the relationship between the
momentum of a photon
and the energy of the photon
anybody know
we've done this a number of times
in fact i think i'm not going to work it
out
let's just state what it is
the energy of a photon is its momentum
times the speed of light let's just
check its units it's easy to check its
units ordinary momentum is mass times
velocity right
all right uh
supposing we multiply that
by another velocity here's momentum and
we're multiplying it by another velocity
then it will have units of mv squared
but mv squared obviously has units of
energy it's the kinetic energy
so momentum times speed of light does
have units of energy and it is the
energy of a photon
its momentum times its velocity
is uh is its energy
so we can rewrite that the force on the
end here
this is the force
that's pc over l
that is the energy
of the photon
divided by the length of the box
well the photon rattles around many many
times and we average over long periods
of time
what is the energy divided by the length
of the box
it's the average energy density
the energy divided by the length the
average energy per unit length
so we found out that the force
in this simple example with just one
photon bag
rattling around the force is just equal
to the energy density and that's it
force
and let's call it rho rho for energy
density but let's keep in mind
that in this example
energy density means energy per unit
length not per unit volume for the
moment
energy density rho
rho stands for energy density is now
supposing there's a lot of photons in
the box
each photon
exerts a force when it bounces into the
end and each photon has an energy
for each photon the force that it exerts
is equal to the energy divided by the
length
so when i add them all up it will still
be true that the total force
will equal the total energy divided by
the length
so this formula is not necessarily the
formula for a single photon
in fact for a single photon it's kind of
a little bit funny because everything
happens in
in jolts that take a long time between
jolts but if you have a lot of photons
in there and all doing the same thing
then it gets smoothed out and the force
or the pressure at the end is simply
equal to the energy density
okay
that's
the one-dimensional case
now let's think about any questions
about this
all right this is a fundamental fact
and it's true in any number of
dimensions not specifically this exact
fact
but similar facts are true in any number
of dimensions that energy density
and
pressure
is are closely related so now let's come
to three dimensions
let's take instead of a
line interval
let's imagine a box
a three-dimensional box
and for the moment
let me suppose that all the molecules
not the molecules the box is full of
photons
uniformly distributed
but
let's
make a simple
wrong assumption
the simple wrong assumption is that all
the photons are moving only along the
x-axis for the moment
suppose they only move along the x-axis
the box is full of photons but let's
take all those photons
in a narrow
what does
what do you call such a shape
a rectangular
parallelopiped i believe
okay let's take all the molecules all
the photons in there and let's assume as
i said wrongly that they're all moving
only in the horizontal direction
then we can say exactly the same things
except we really should say it in the
following way
let's take a little element of area here
here's a little element of area
and take all of the photons in that
little element of area
i'm not going to write that as rho times
the length because i'm now going to
think of rho
as
oh i'm sorry i'm i'm not going yes i'm
going to think of rho
as the density per three-dimensional
volume
all right
what is
the cost what is the corresponding
formula
well you can write it the same way
the force
is equal it is in fact equal to the
energy in that rectangular hyperbola
uh divided by the length that hasn't
changed
but now i want to divide both sides of
this oh sorry that's divided by the
length
now i want to divide both sides of this
by the little element of area
so let's divide it by the little element
of area there
a stands for a small area now
and now what's the length times the area
that's the volume in this region here
what's the force divided by the area
that's the pressure
that's the definition of pressure force
per unit area
so we come to
pressure
not momentum now
i think i use small p for momentum
pressure
is equal again
to energy divided by volume
which is again rho
but now this doesn't mean energy per
unit length it means energy per unit
volume now what's wrong with this
this is a funny setup here
i have pressure on the ends of the box
here but if there are no particles going
vertically
bouncing off the roof and the floor
there will be no pressure on the roof
and the floor
we know from experience that uh that a
nice thermalized distribution of
molecules or photons or whatever they
are will exert equal pressures in all
directions
so
let's imagine now here's a here's an
oversimplification but it's closer to
our truth let's suppose that there are
photons which move along the x-axis
photons which move along the y-axis
and photons which move along the z axis
this of course is still an
oversimplification
the typical photon will be moving in
some oblique direction which is neither
x y or z
but let's just take this simple case
here where there are equal density of
photons
moving vertically horizontally and in
and out
same density of photons and what will
the right equation be
well only those photons which are moving
horizontally
will contribute to the pressure on
the
on this wall
only those moving vertically will
contribute to the pressure on the
ceiling
only those moving in and out will
contribute to the pressure on the front
wall
so what's the right formula the right
formula is the pressure
is equal to the energy density
divided by three
one third of the photons are moving this
way they all have energy
all of them have energy
but only a third of them contribute to
each component of the pressure
so the formula would be
in this uh
oversimplified setup
row divided by three
now
is this the
the setup was oversimplified the answer
is correct
the answer is correct
the answer is correct no matter what
directions the photons are moving in as
long as they're
as long as they're all scrambled up
enough
the right answer of course
is a given photon is moving in some
random direction
but it has an x component of momentum a
y component the momentum and a z
component of momentum
the total
energy uh
is whatever the total energy is but it
works exactly as if a third the photons
are moving this way a third the photons
are moving this way and a third of the
photons are moving the other way so this
is a correct relationship but i don't
want to i don't want to do it in detail
it is a correct relationship
really it's just that on the average a
third of the energy is going into motion
in this direction a third is going into
historic and so forth all right so p
equals rho over 3.
let's write that down over here
pressure
for the radiation-dominated world
is energy density
radiation
divided by three
what about the matter dominated world
the matter dominated world
is a world in which atoms are there
or galaxies objects are there
but relative to the box the box if you
want to imagine what the box is the box
is a certain region of space that's
moving along with the flow
the atoms are not moving or whatever is
making up the material is not moving
relative to the walls of the box
they're frozen they start they're stuck
do they have energy density sure each
one has a mass multiply the mass by m c
squared no don't multiply the mass by m
c squared multiply the mass by c squared
and you will find the energy of each one
but what about the pressure is it
exerting any pressure on the walls of
the box
no because they're not banging into the
walls of the box they're standing still
they don't exert any force on the walls
of the box
so this limit
of very slowly moving particles moving
with the flow
corresponds to pressure equals zero
are there other possibilities sure we
could heat up this material
so that the molecules were moving more
or so that the galaxies were moving more
then we would have some pressure
and we could get sort of halfway in
between we could have we could have a
parameter
the temperature of what's going on in
here
when the molecules are cold
hydrogen is cold or the galaxies are uh
um
cold what does cold mean
cold doesn't mean that the stars are
cold
it means that they're not moving
relative to the uh
to the
ambient background
cold molecules don't exert pressure
fast molecules exert pressure
speed of light sort of as a limiting
case
uh the pressure is uh fairly large yeah
in the case of expanding universe right
now
yes they are but take a small enough box
take a small box uh so that we don't
have to worry about the growth of it and
examine this for an infinite decimal box
for an infinite decimal box this uh
this will work
okay so here we have p
equals rho over three radiation over
three here we have p equals zero
and i'm going to write a more general
equation
i'm going to write the equation
that the pressure this doesn't
not associated with this third line yet
let's erase the third line we don't know
about the third line yet
not eraser just put it down here
row naught
let me write a general equation it's an
equation which covers a lot of different
assumptions
it is the pressure
is proportional
to the energy density rho whatever the
energy density is
times a numerical factor w
what is w for the cold gas
zero
w equals zero
what is w over here
a third
w is a parameter
which when you vary it from one thing to
another you can cover a lot of ground
about what the material which is driving
the uh the universe is
for example something between zero and
one-third
would describe something called warm
dark matter if dark dark matter is not
thought to be warm dark matter is
thought to be just as cold and
correspond to p equals zero
but
for a while people thought that dark
matter might correspond to neutrinos
neutrinos move pretty fast they whizz
back and forth
and
they don't quite move with the speed of
light
and if that was what the dark matter was
then we wouldn't have p equals zero
because the neutrinos would be moving we
wouldn't quite have p equals uh w equals
a third because that corresponds to
motion with the speed of light you
enough something a little bit less than
a third
so
there's a wide variety of different
kinds this is called the equation of
state
w is the parameter in the equation of
uh just that's just terminology and w is
just
terminology but if you want to follow
what's going on in cosmology
and
the article says well something or other
called w and astronomers are measuring
it to equal something or other or
something or other you want to know what
it is
so that's what w is
okay so that uh that covers
the different
kinds of equations of state
but now let's come
to yeah i want to continue with this
line of reasoning about the equation of
state
how is w
related notice that there's a
relationship or could be a relationship
between what w is when w is equal to
zero
it looks like the energy density
goes like one over a cubed
when w is equal to one third it looks
like it goes one one over eight to the
fourth is there a pattern there is there
some reason
that as you vary this w
the energy
momentum sorry the energy pressure
ratio
is there some reason that that governs
how the energy density changes with a
and the answer is yes there is a
relationship i'm going to show it to you
uh
[Music]
it's tricky
it's not hard no fancy no fancy
mathematics no fancy calculus just
subtle
it's a little bit subtle
a little bit of calculus but nothing
fancy
but
[Music]
some subtle reasoning
it's called thermodynamics and
thermodynamics is always hard
not because it's mathematically hard
this is very easy thermodynamics but
nevertheless
a little bit hard
let's take a box
this box does not have to be a cube it
could be any shape whatever
all right and expand the box a little
bit
we could expand the box by moving one
wall out a little bit we can move all
three walls out a little bit
but what we're doing is just increasing
the volume of the box
molecules on the inside
molecules or
photons or whatever
there may or may not be and typically
there will be pressure on the walls of
the
box pressure on the walls of the box
when we move the walls of the box we do
some work
on the walls the pressure on the inside
pushes against the wall
and does some work
how much work does it do let's see if we
can figure out how much work is that
supposing this wall moves
by a little distance called dx
only the x wall moves a little bit we
move the x well a little bit how much
work is done
on the x wall
by moving it a little distance dx
force times the x that's the work done
what's the force
pressure times area so the work done
on the walls of the box
is the pressure
times the x
times the area of the wall
what is dx times a
that's the change in the volume of the
box
so it's pressure
times the change in the volume of the
box
you would get the same thing if you
moved the vertical
dimension a little bit or the in out
direction a little bit in fact you would
get the same thing if you changed all
the directions simultaneously
the work done
is the pressure times the change in the
volume
now
where does what does that work where
does that work come from
uh energy conservation tells you that
that what does that work that work is
the increase in the energy of the walls
of the box where did it come from
it came
from it got robbed
or the the the internal energy in the
gas
whether it be photons or whatever it is
got robbed of a little bit of energy
and that energy went into work
the energy in the box decreased that is
why the temperature of a box goes down
when you increase the size of the box
the internal energy decreases
so we can write the decrease in the
energy of the box
is pdv why the minus sign
because the energy of the box goes down
a little bit
all right this is a very general fact
about gases of all kinds
that the change in the internal energy
when you just shift the walls a little
bit
is
just pdv this could be a spherical box
let's take it could be a spherical box
it could be a cubicle box it doesn't
matter
and we might also write
that
well later on yeah let's do it now no no
let's leave it this way for a moment
later on we're going to write that the
volume of the box is a cubed
a being the scale factor
later on we'll think of this as a box
one scale factor on a side but for the
time being it's just that
now what is the energy in the box the
energy in the box
is the energy density times the volume
right e is energy density times volume
so what is the change in energy
if energy is
rho times v
and we don't know offhand row may change
a little bit we know that the energy is
going to change
it may change because row changes or it
may change because the volume of the box
or maybe both
so we should write
that the change in the energy of the box
is equal
to rho
dv
plus v
d rho
that's just the change in a product when
you change each term each factor a
little bit
just elementary calculus d e equals rho
dv plus v d rho
and that's equal
to minus p dv
let's take everything with a dv with a d
volume and put it on the right hand side
then we get volume
times dp
is equal
to minus
p
plus rho
times dv
v d rho sorry v d rho
i have written in my notes here which
you will get the copy of over the
interval or something
i have p equals one third row someplace
and then i put in brackets p p e e
equals one third row r h row so that i
wouldn't make that mistake
[Music]
oh
right
row and p are not the same thing
v
d rho equals right there's a there's
that equation now let's remember now
that for a lot of interesting situations
the
where is it
that p
is related to the energy density
by a numerical number w
which happens to be one-third for
photons happens to be zero for cold uh
motionless matter and it could be other
things
so let's plug that in
let's plug that in
and we get an equation
v d rho
is equal to minus
now let's say
p
is w times rho so i think i will write
that this is w
plus 1
uh
rho
d dv does everybody see what i've done
i've simply said
that w times rho is equal to p
if i happen to know what w is
then this equation can be nicely solved
let me show you the solution the
solution we write i'm going to do a
little bit of differential equations
here
we can write d rho over rho
is equal to minus
w plus 1 w now is a number
w is a number dv divided by v
i've divided by v and i've divided by
rho
all right for those who know enough
calculus what is d row over row
it's the differential change in
log of rho
so this is the change in log of rho
minus
w plus one what's dv over v
d of log v
this is not very hard to solve
it says that log of rho
is equal whoops minus
equals minus w plus 1
log of v
what uh
the right hand side if i multiply
something by the logarithm of v that's
equal to the logarithm of something else
logarithm of
v
to our power
minus w plus one
all right
in other words one over v
to the w plus one
no i don't think so
oh uh
uh
yeah there's an additive constant
yeah there's a one can add a constant
won't change anything
okay what's the solution to this
rho is equal to one divided by volume to
the w plus one let's just write
just throw away the log cancel out the
logarithms
rho is equal
to one divided by the volume
to the w plus one
let me just remind you what we use we
basically used energy conservation
that the work done in expanding the box
is the energy
that is robbed from the internal energy
and then we used the relationship
between internal energy and pressure
pressure to tell us the work
and
that's this is the equation
the e equals pdv
and then we used for energy rho times
volume and for pressure
w times energy density and that told us
that the density
behaves like one over the volume this
tells us
how the energy density changes as we
change the size of the box
all right now what box are we talking
about we're talking about a box so we
could be talking about a box
which is one unit
on a side in cosmology
one coordinate unit on the side
one coordinate unit on the side but a
box which is one coordinate unit on a
side in a small amount of time will
expand
when that box expands we apply exactly
this rule here and what does it tell us
it tells us that rho
what's the volume of the box
proportional to a cube but if i take a
box which is one unit on the side
its volume is a cubed
so what does it tell me well there's a
constant here there's a numerical
constant
a numerical constant divided by a to the
w plus one
that tells me how the energy density
changes as you expand the box
well
did i get it right no i didn't get it
right
there's a three
it's a cubed w v is eight cubed so it's
three w plus three
did i do that right no three
yeah three w plus three
no no it's not three w plus three what
is
uh i've lost something
there's a four in there where's my four
um
three times one plus w that's that seems
right three times one plus w
yeah that's right three times one plus w
okay let's try it out
w here's w equals zero that's
matter cold matter
w equals zero
c divided by a cubed w is equal to zero
one plus w is one
c divided by a cubed that's exactly this
formula here
so we've got a very very fancy argument
just to tell us
that if we have a bunch of unmoving
particles which exert no pressure
that the energy density
decreases like one over a cubed duh
okay let's try it for radiation
for radiation w is equal to a third
this is one plus a third is four thirds
divided by three is four that's a little
less da
a over four
so for radiation it's a over 4
but now you'll have the tools
to decide exactly how rho behaves given
any equation of state an equation of
state means a value of w
so you could have other kinds of
material
other kinds of warm gas cold gas other
kinds of mixtures of gases whatever
for which w might be some other number
if so
you simply plug into this formula and
this will tell you how rho changes with
a what good does that do you
well you couple it up again
with the
frw equation of motion whereas we've
erased it i think we don't need this
anymore
this was the final conclusion
and it's the reason this tells you why w
is an interesting quantity in cosmology
tells you how the energy density changes
as the universe expands
remember
we have a dot over a
squared
is equal to
eight thirds
pi
g
times rho
so once we know how rho depends on a we
can put it into here
and now with a little bit of work
or we put some constant
divided by a
cubed to the 1 plus w
now with a little bit of work you should
be able to tell me how a depends on time
for a given
w do we do that we just try out
different power laws
t to the two thirds t to the one half
i'm going to leave that for you
all you have to do is plug in
a goes like t to a power
plug it into this equation and require
that the left hand side and the right
hand side balance
and you'll find that this power i don't
remember the detailed relation this
power depends on w
when w is equal to
zero
this power is two-thirds when w is equal
to a half the power is um
one-half no no when w is equal to a
third
radiation
yeah
okay so you can work that out yourself
and you can find out how the universe
expands
for any value of w
with one exception
what's the exception
well you may have a little bit of
trouble
yeah you might have a little bit of
trouble with minus one
right with w equals minus one
what is w equals minus one does it mean
anything
and is there an answer to the problem
yeah
w equals minus one
we'll see why
is exactly this vacuum energy here
the vacuum energy which doesn't grow
or shrink or do anything
uh w equals minus one
just means if you look at it w equals
minus one
that's a to the zero power right
if w equals minus 1
that says that the energy density
doesn't depend on a at all
one plus w in that case would be zero
and we would just have c divided by a to
the zero
and a to the zero
is just doesn't depend on a
all right
so w equals minus one
is exactly the situation
where
rho
is constant
where rho simply doesn't change
when you expand the universe it's the
situation where
the energy doesn't dilute
it's as if you keep putting in new
things
as the universe expands to make up for
the separate for the increased um
distance between things
all right is it an interesting situation
yes it is a very interesting situation
it corresponds to
einstein's cosmological constant it
corresponds to what's called dark energy
or uh vacuum energy
so
it's worth a while to spend a little bit
of time
uh
working out
what happens when w is equal to zero no
when w is equal to minus one
incidentally w equals minus one
you might say wait that's weird
that means that the pressure
is minus the energy density
well the energy density is positive this
is not the energy density being negative
the pressure is negative
is pressure being negative weird how
weird is pressure being negative
well if you have two walls positive
pressure means
pushing against the walls if you have
two walls connected by a rubber band you
have to pull them apart
they're being pulled together that's
negative pressure all negative pressure
is is tension a resistance against
against expansion
so negative pressure is a perfectly good
thing you take a rubber band and you
stretch it and it's an example of
negative pressure it's pulling the ends
together positive pressure is that which
pushes against the ends so negative
pressure is in itself not weird
uh
as i said it corresponds to a kind of
tension
it's certainly not mathematically
strange
and it's common in physics
pressure tension
the same thing one is just the opposite
of the other in sign
okay so let's work out
how the frw equation behaves
if
w is equal to minus one
in that case
the energy density is just constant
so let's just plug in that the energy
density is constant and we've already
named it we've called it rho zero
rho zero is a constant it doesn't by
constant i mean it doesn't depend on
time it's it's a constant of nature if
you like
it's something which you measure and it
never changes why doesn't it change
because it doesn't dilute
whoops
okay
the combination just as again i hate
terminology there's too much terminology
we can't help it
because things get named independently
by different people and eventually
we just have too many names for things
the combination eight pi g
rho naught has another name
anybody know what it is
lambda
rho naught is called vacuum energy
lambda is called cosmological constant
they are the same thing apart from some
numerical factors
whenever there is a cosmological
constant it means there's a vacuum
energy whenever there's a vacuum energy
it means it's a cosmological constant
now
why lambda was not named 8 pi g over
three times rho naught
that's a historical uh
fact we'll
we'll find out why einstein didn't
include the three here
uh there's no interesting physics in it
um yeah
i'll tell you what the interesting
physics is
einstein's equations actually look like
this
so when einstein wrote his equations it
was natural for him to define this thing
over here
but
when he solved the equations
not he but when the sitter solved the
equations he put the 3 over here
[Music]
so
lambda is by definition not the right
hand side of this equation there's an
extra factor of 3.
all right
remember the right hand side is just a
number
the right hand side is just a number
don't think about how it changes or
anything it's seven or six or five or
whatever it is and some units or other
and we can take a square root and we can
write that a dot
over a
is equal to the square root of this
number 8 pi g over 3 rho naught
or
a dot
is a times a number
what's the solution to an equation like
a dot is proportional to a
and exponential
the time rate of change of a
is proportional to an exponential now of
course
the combination a pi g over 3
the square root of it
8 pi g rho
over 3
has yet another name
okay
let me tell you what the other name is
but we don't know i can tell you what
the other name is very quickly let's put
it back in this form here do you
remember what a dot over a is in general
it's the hubble constant
but of course the hubble constant is not
typically a constant
but in this case it is a constant
in this case the hubble this is the
unique special case w equals minus one
where the hubble constant really is a
constant
and it doesn't change with time this is
rho naught i'm sorry
rho naught
so it's sometimes just called h
but if i call it h we'll lose track of
the fact that that
h already is something which can change
with time and so forth so i'm just going
to call it this
and our equation is the time rate of
change of a
is proportional to a with a numerical
coefficient
what's the solution a equals
a constant times
what
no no not wrong not hey
e exponential exponential when the rate
of change of something is proportional
to the thing
that's when you have an exponential an
exponential growth the rate of change is
proportional to the thing itself
all right
and what's the thing in the exponential
e to the
it's going to be e to the time but
there's a time constant
and the time constant is just the square
root here
square root
a dot over a squared came from the
square there
not a cube root
what's
that rho naught oops
rho naught inside the square root
all right
let me write it over so it's clear
e to the square root of 8
pi
g
rho naught divided by 3 all of which is
a number
times t
so
if there is a vacuum energy
if there is a component of the energy
well if
here we're just doing pure vacuum energy
in a few minutes we'll talk about what
happens
if all three of them are present
simultaneously
but if there was only a vacuum energy
the universe would exponentially expand
and it would expand
at a rate which is governed by this rho
naught
now
the universe it doesn't expand doesn't
double in size
this is not the
e to this number here or this number
here
is not the doubling time it's called the
e folding time it's the amount that's
the amount of time that it takes the
universe to expand by a factor of e
but it's sort of like the doubling time
the doubling time for the universe is
not a second and it's not a thousandth
of a second and it's not 10 to the minus
43 seconds the doubling time for the
universe is pretty darn slow
uh
what's roughly speaking the doubling
time of the universe
something about
some of the five 10 billion years
of order of order the age of the
universe which is which sounds like an
accident and it doesn't seem like an
accident
more or less accidental at the present
time
that the age of the universe and the
doubling time are about the same
that means that rho naught is very very
small
rho naught thought of as an ordinary
energy density is very very small
but of course what it's competing with
is other very small energy densities
the energy density in the universe due
to ordinary matter in galaxies and so
forth is very very small
galaxies are far apart
and so uh the question comes up which
one of these is present
the answer is all of them
and let's uh discuss
well let's first of all add this in
row naught
equals i'm just going to write rho
naught
this is called vacuum
dominant
the vacuum dominated universe
and it's a is equal
to e
for the square root of 8 pi g rho naught
3. i'm not going to write it times t
exponentially increasing and this
corresponds to w equals minus 1.
p equals minus rho
okay that's the basic idea of vacuum
energy
doesn't that mean that eventually he's
going to grow very small
at the back and it doesn't mean what it
does it doesn't mean that eventually
it's exponential it'll overwhelm the
other two
expansions
so
well
no it doesn't mean necessarily
everything will rip apart
um
if you're holding hands
with your mate
and there's a weak tendency or a small
exponential growth
it's not going to tail your partners
away from you
your grip
may be stronger than the tendency for
the expansion to pull him or her away
from you
um
so no it won't necessarily pull
everything apart
but
what won't get pulled apart is the
clumpiness
on some average scale on some long
distance scale a scale which is large
enough
that the gravity holding things together
is too weak to hold them together yes it
will pull everything apart it won't pull
apart our galaxy
our galaxy is concentrated and and dense
enough
and sort of well above average energy
density
so well above average energy density
that it's being pulled together in fact
it won't pull the solar system apart it
won't pull an atom apart
but it will pull apart a supercluster or
a sufficiently big
uh sample
and so it's it's a delicate question of
what gets pulled upon and what doesn't
and we could try to be quantitative
about that and maybe i'll come back to
it
but on the average over very large
scales yes things will get all get
pulled apart by this effect
okay so
um
question that last line uh a equals e to
the times that that implies no
asymptotic limit does it does that imply
and that's the vacuum in the vacuum line
this is it asymptotically
right
but
there's no upper
over a little distance is supposed to
hurt this thing is very far apart this
is very large
yeah eventually
but again
over small enough distances it's
counteracted by other forces
this can be modeled
by a weak force
pulling things apart
on the average if things were far enough
apart and dilute enough
everything would expand with it
but there may be places where
the energy density is sort of
concentrated in lumps
those lumps may have enough internal
gravity to hold them together
so instead of the lumps expanding the
lump might even contract but distant
lumps will fly apart
so there is a lumpiness to the universe
the universe is doing two things
simultaneously
the lumpiness is contracting ever into
more lumpiness
but meanwhile on larger scales
everything is separating and uh
and becoming more dilute
yeah
okay so
dark matter
is a no not radiation is part of this
there are two components
to the matter energy density
one of which is familiar matter it's the
stuff which shines in the sky
and the rest of it is dark matter
what do we say dark matter is about 10
times as much as ordinary matter
but it has the same equation of state
and so from the overall behavior
or just from the overall behavior
without knowing more all you can say is
there's a certain amount of matter yeah
now is there anything uh interesting in
the
negative side in front of that square
root
well i mean
you know when you take the square root
oh
yeah there are two possible solutions
there are always two possible solutions
does the universe and the universe run
backward
universe run backward contracts
there's always the equations are always
such that they admit two solutions
the forward-going
thing and the thing which you would
watch if you ran the movie backward
they're always both solutions
and it comes from the fact there's a
square here so when you solve for a dot
over a you take a square root it could
be positive or negative
physically of course they're the same
but they correspond to watching it going
forward or watching it going backward
is that actually a question
well it's not a contracting universe
then
it's not a question of whether
no
no okay
the universe
let's forget for the moment this vacuum
energy
in any case you always have two
solutions
now
what are the two solutions
you
see an object
far from the earth
and it has a certain kinetic energy
and a certain potential energy
how is it moving
well all you can tell from its kinetic
energy is what its overall
overall speed is
you can't tell whether it's moving away
from the earth or toward the earth
if you know something you know you we we
see a it's not a satellite it's not
going around but you see a distant
object moving radially
moving radially
we know it's kinetic energy
is it moving toward us or is it moving
away from us you can't tell unless you
know an additional piece of information
namely whether it's moving away from you
or toward you its kinetic energy doesn't
tell you
this is basically an equation telling
you about the kinetic energy of
something receding
it could be positive or could be
negative
things
given
where it is
it doesn't help to say that the earth
attracts that doesn't mean that the
object far away is moving toward you
it simply means that it may it may
decelerate if it's going away it may
decelerate but there's no way that you
can know whether it's moving away from
you or toward you that's an additional
piece of information
all right the additional piece of
information is at least with a normal
concept of things
the universe is expanding with ordinary
time
whatever we're contracting with ordinary
time would we know the difference
hard to tell
no no i mean
well if everything was running backwards
including us
obviously we couldn't tell
right we would just be part of a movie
running backwards and uh
we would speak backwards we would think
backwards
right so
turning uh it would just be a it would
just be a change of variables from t to
minus t right so there's always that
ambiguity in the equations
and we always pick out more or less by
definition the expanding solution
okay
the expanding solution
what is it that determines the direction
of time when we say the future versus
the past
it's thermodynamics
so it's a second law of thermodynamics
but we won't get into that today
uh there certainly is ordinarily a
difference between past and future but
let's not do that now
all right let's uh let's let's summarize
now the three components of
matter in the universe these are all
called matter
even though this is just plain vacuum
they're all called
again ambiguities of uh of terminology
that's matter that's radiation that's
vacuum
all right but collectively they're all
called matter
maybe we should just call it stuff
stuff let's call it stuff
all right
matter meaning this
has two components dark matter and
luminous matter
of which there is more dark matter
the radiation today
is very very weak because it's been
red-shifted but at some time in the past
when the universe was about a thousand
times smaller
because of the difference in the way
the radiation depends on scale factor
at some time in the past the radiation
was the dominant component
and in the future
the long time future
as the universe expands
both of these will get smaller and
smaller and this does not get smaller
and smaller so in the remote future
the expansion of the universe will be
governed by the vacuum energy
all right let's draw some graphs just to
uh just to illustrate
i'm drawing these graphs because these
are the kind of graphs you'll see if you
read a scientific american article
unfortunately astronomers and
astrophysicists have this terrible habit
of taking simple graphs and
superimposing them upon each other until
you have so many things on the graph
that you can't possibly figure out
what's going on
but you could take them apart and say
you know
i'm taking the graphs apart and one by
one all right
no i know i'm not going to take them
apart i'm going to put them on top of
each other i'm going to be an
astrophysicist today
all right
we could plot
as a function of scale factor this is a
function of the
expansion of the universe
we could plot energy density and there
are three kinds of energy densities and
let's put all three of them on the same
graph it does help to put them on the
same graph
all right we can start with the easiest
one the easiest one
is
rho naught it's just constant
it does not depend on a at all we're not
talking about now a is a function of
time
we're talking about rho as a function of
a it's just constant
it looks like that
it doesn't dilute diluting would mean
going to zero
now let's take
radiation i'm working upward
radiation
is very big when a is small
and very small when a is big
right so it falls off quickly
here's radiation
it falls off
quickly
now finally in sort of in between is
matter
let's make matter in blue
matter falls off like 1 over a cubed
that means that small a it's smaller
than the radiation component
but at large a it's larger and so it
crosses over
it crosses over
but also goes to zero eventually
let's imagine now
all right so there's a crossover point
here
at that point that's the point at which
the universe goes from being radiation
dominated to being matter dominated
right that happened after about 10 000
years
very very early in the history of the
universe
the universe was very very hot
much too hot to be transparent and so we
can't directly look back to that point
it was about a hundred thousand years in
other words another factor of ten later
when the universe became transparent
it's in here someplace
but this is the crossover from matter
let's write down this is radiation
this is matter
this is vacuum
and then later on when the universe got
bigger
there was a crossover between matter and
vacuum
uh what's the total energy density well
very early it was dominated by
radiation
so let's get a red pen here let's
very early it was mostly just radiation
so it was this
then when it crossed over it was mostly
matter the radiation became less
important and it tracked along here well
eventually it just moved on to this line
but then if we waited long enough
the
both of these became smaller than the
vacuum energy and so it gradually
shifted and just became vacuum energy so
there were three eras if you like the
radiation dominated era
everything was much too hot to be uh to
be transparent
the matter dominated era
where
most interesting things
of cosmology happened
but not life
life formed
someplace around here where the
crossover happened
this crossover is about i don't know if
it's four million years four billion
years five six billion years
some number of billions of years of
order of magnitude the age of the
universe
so more or less we're in the transition
region
more on the vacuum side
than on the matter side
in here somewheres
but we're in this transition region
now let's uh let's talk how do we know
this what are what's the observations
that tell us that this
sequence is what happened
and for that we look at another graph
the other graph
is not energy density
versus scale factor but scale factor
versus time it's simply the time history
of the universe
and how it grew
so here it is
early on
the dominant form of energy was
radiation the others were negligible
and the implication is
that the universe grew like t to the
one-half
t to the one-half is a parabola turned
on its side
so if there was only radiation
it would go like that
but then at some point the crossover
matter
became more important than radiation
but still
sorry it's more important than anything
still more important than vacuum
and it became more important than
radiation
and at that point
when i say point of course i mean
a range of times
but over a range of times let's put it
in here somewheres
it
made a transition
and instead of
going like t to the one half
it went like t to the two thirds
it didn't have a bump like that in it
but uh that's
so it made a transition from t to the
one half to t to the two thirds as i
said we can't see back that far it
happened too early so let's put it early
t to the one half
then
t to the two thirds
and then somewhere is in here something
very dramatic happened
instead of following something like this
the universe began
to expand in an accelerated way
why is it called accelerated it's called
accelerated because exponential
expansion
and exponential
is accelerated that's uh what does
acceleration means it means the second
derivative second time derivative of
something
[Music]
the second time derivative of an
exponential is as big as the exponential
itself so it's accelerated expansion
but just exponential expansion
where are we
where somewheres around over here maybe
a little bit further out
we've seen enough of this exponential
to know that it's there
we've seen enough of the exponential to
be pretty sure that it's behaving like
an exponential
at the present time
but how do we see these different
behaviors
all we have now we're at a certain time
how do we see
we can't see the future
but we can see the past
and the way we see the past is by
looking out with large telescopes
out to
distances that correspond to earlier
times
so when we look far out and we count
galaxies and we see how the galaxies are
moving and how their motion correlates
with their distance
effectively we're measuring
what we're measuring is the hubble
constant as a function of time
but equivalently we're measuring this
whole curve
we can't see
back
directly to the radiation-dominated era
most people believe it was there
but we can certainly see the
matter-dominated era
and the transition to the uh
to the cosmological constant dominated
era
so
[Music]
so this is sort of looking at a certain
distance and measuring the couple
constant and for that distance at that
time and then a later time and earlier
time and you get this curve once you're
done with it
so it's a reconstruction but it's not a
very difficult reconstruction
if you
what's difficult is the observations
but once you have the observations and
you've cleared out all the garbage and
the
systematic errors and everything else
it's a relatively simple matter to
reconstruct uh
to reconstruct the time history of the
of the scale factor
and it is
completely consistent with this
transition from matter dominated to uh
to cosmological constant dominated
as far as we know
this is really tending to a pure
exponential
we don't know anything else that looks
that looks like that
and what that means is the universe is
going to exponentially increase
apart from those things which are
attached to us by gravitational cords or
other kinds of
strong forces
things which are sufficiently far away
that they're
participating in this overall expansion
those things will eventually just
disappear through the horizon
i haven't told you yet about the horizon
but now it's easy to it's now easy to
figure out what the horizon is
um yeah let's uh let's see if we can
understand now the idea of the horizon
i have a good question about that
because there seems to be
an indication of what you said earlier
the surface of black scattering
[Music]
well the surface of last scattering
um
it's not moving
it's the place where the radiation
well sorry
yeah it is moving um as time goes on
the surface of glass scattering will
move out
and but it will never get past the
horizon
in other words we will see the rate the
radiation that we will see
will be coming as our own time goes on
the radiation will be coming from a
place which gradually moves out
which is equivalent to the radiation
cooling
we will see a cooler and cooler universe
which is equivalent to the universe
expanding how is that different from
the local galaxies moving beyond the
horizon
no it's it's it's not the same thing
at a later time
the radiation that we see will not come
from the same atoms
as the radiation that we see now
it will come from atoms which were
further away at that time
so it's uh like seeing deeper and deeper
and deeper uh
into the universe rather than seeing
something moving away from us
just put the chronological factor on
this thinking on this like 50 years ago
it was about the time when they
determined
the early portion of the universe right
the big bang theory started
it was kind of clear about it
and that predates my high school
education
it was the late 1560s
dominated
matter dominated was believed
to be the way the universe is young
there's another difference also
the other difference is what we have
left out so far where's the frw equation
we're going to put it back next time
a dot over a squared is equal to rho
i'm leaving out 8 pi over 3 blah blah
and g
row times stuff and then there was that
other thing minus k over a squared
remember that
we've left that out
now numerically it seems to be very
insignificant and so leaving it out
seems okay numerically
but it really is conceptually important
it determines whether the universe is
closed and bounded
or whether it's open or whatever it's
doing
now in the old days before there was a
cosmological constant
and it was believed that the universe
was closed and bounded so that this term
was there
then
people would have drawn curves which
look like this
they would have drawn curves where the
universe expands for a while and then
recontracts
and followed by a crunch
this is nothing but the phenomena of
something going up and then coming back
down
right k here tells you whether the total
energy is positive or negative
k equals zero is right at the escape
velocity
so in the early days of big bang
cosmology
it was assumed the universe was closed
and bounded which meant that k had a
certain sign
and nobody knew about vacuum energy
einstein had rejected his uh his uh his
child as uh
a bad mistake
and so it was thought that the universe
was matter dominated
with a net total energy
below zero
which means
that just like this thing will come back
down the universe would crash
this was called the big crunch and this
was the big bang
now we don't believe in this part
anymore
not that we don't believe in it
mathematically there was nothing wrong
with it
but empirically
this k seems to be zero to a high
approximation
and there's a component in the energy
which is driving this accelerated
expansion
so to the best of our knowledge the
universe is not going to crash
i missed the time when the transition to
the exponential occurring
it's somewhere in the vicinity of about
five billion years ago
both are going from the beginning
remember the universe is about 10
billion years old
oh okay i i don't remember
it's a fuzzy beginning
it's a fuzzy beginning but it's order of
magnitude the age of the universe half
the age of the universe
yeah
uh somebody might look it up and i i
don't have the number of bodies
two quick ones one is that vacuum energy
related to quantum vacuum yes
or at least we believe it is
yes all right let me just tell you one
more thing today
these energy densities scale differently
with time
1 of a cube 1 over a 4th
but today
today you can ask what is the relative
abundance or the relative magnitude of
the different components of energy
so i'll tell you what the relative
abundance are
now that you know what they mean
relative not absolute but i could also
tell you absolute but uh but relative
abundance the biggest single one is the
vacuum energy
rho naught
let's write rho naught over rho total
okay
this just means the fractional row total
means the sum of all the energy
densities this is today today
is about 70 percent
0.7
so most of the energy that means that we
are well into the region dominated by uh
by the vacuum but not that well i mean
it's not you know it's not the it's not
0.999
the vacuum energy it's 0.7
okay today
uh rome matter
is today
about
point three
row radiation
is negligible
very very small
about
i think about ten thousand times smaller
than the matter energy so this is very
very small essentially zero not much
there
but the raw matter
comes in two pieces
row dark
plus row let's call it luminous
the dark matter well let's see the
luminous is about five percent 0.05
and this i guess is about .25
that's the composition today
that's the composition today if you run
it backward or forward
the ratio of dark matter and luminous
matter will stay the same that's because
they both
scale like one over a cubed that'll stay
the same
so
[Music]
the ratio between these two but oh i
should i'm sorry i should i should
divide by row total
over row total
but depending on the error on the time
the relative abundance of these three
will be different if you go into the
remote past radiation dominated
if you go into the mid past the moderate
past matter dominated go into the remote
future this will become essentially one
and it'll all be
vacuum energy
at which point the universe will just
exponentially increase
[Music]
uh cooling as it increases and
it's interesting to think about the
astronomers of that period
[Music]
they will
they will live in the universe and look
around them and see nothing except for
the except for the immediate galaxies
which will be in falling toward them
uh the uh i think the andromeda and the
uh magellanic clouds are about the only
thing that they'll see out there and by
that time they will have merged anyway
so they'll see a single galaxy this will
be about 100 billion years they'll take
100 150 billion years or something like
that
our galaxy will be completely isolated
oh another question is where is the
horizon how far away is the horizon
so
to figure out where the horizon is what
we want to do is figure out what the
hubble constant is let's figure out the
hubble constant
here we have it
a
well let's just write down the equation
a dot over a
is equal to
what is it um
uh square root
8 pi
g
over 3
rho naught
that's it
that's the hubble constant did i get
everything i think so
yeah
uh and in the future
and in the future in the remote future
there will only be rho naught
so this is not quite true today the
other energies are in there but in the
future
wait a little while
mostly it'll just be rho naught and this
will be the form of the equation this is
also the hubble constant
and so if we write
the equation that hubble originally
wrote
namely
our velocity is equal to distance times
hubble
square root of 8 pi g over 3 rho naught
then we can ask the question how far
away do you have to be
so that the outward recessional velocity
is the speed of light
and all you have to do is substitute
speed of light in there
one in our units one
and that tells you
that the distance to the horizon the
distance to where things are moving away
from you with the speed of light
is 1 over
square root of 8 pi g over 3 rho naught
it's this distance which is about 10 12
billion light years away
but notice that it doesn't change with
time
once this exponential expansion sets in
the hubble constant stays constant
and the distance to the horizon is just
fixed
what is the horizon
the horizon is where things are moving
away from us with the speed of light
so as the galaxies in the universe
expands one by one
the galaxies
will pass through this horizon and we
can just wave goodbye to them
uh they will get so actually what will
happen to them is they'll get more and
more and more red-shifted
until we just can't see them anymore
that will happen to just about
everything with the exception of the
nearby magellanic clouds in an andromeda
galaxy
so the astronomers of that period unless
they have good history books to remind
them of what people knew in the past
would be very puzzled they will think
that
the universe is an island in an
otherwise infinite sea of empty space
they will not be able to see the uh the
black body
microwave background radiation it will
be too
thinned out too red-shifted
they will have no way of even knowing
there's a cosmological constant because
they won't see anything receding away
from them there will be nothing out
there
so
we can imagine them being very puzzled
and thinking that the universe was uh
was one galaxy and nothing else read the
early books
read the early books
if the early books are still um
that's actually very hard to keep
information over long periods of time
if you just look at our brief history
all right back to literacy
someone back there that uh
there may have been other terms
and and they said
well you know it's only year three
and they say well in in year 5 billion
they're they're going to only see this
this and this right
it would be extremely hard for the
astronomers at year three
to know that there was a cosmological
constant because it was so much so
subdominant
but
it's also true that there were no
astronomers at year three because it was
too hot
it's a curious fact that um that the
cosmological all the cosmological
parameters point to about the same
scale of time
as the evolutionary time scale for
evolving a uh
for an evolving a human being
uh you know
a couple of billion a couple of billion
years to go from
well first of all you've got to get the
sun to cool i mean you got to get the
sun to form and so forth that takes a
couple of a billion years or so
but then the time scale for evolution is
what three billion years or something
for four or five billion or four billion
years
yeah you got to get the metals
so the time scale for evolution of a
complex organism
was about 4 billion years
the first three billion of which
was simple single cell things yeah and
it required stability of things for that
long revolution to take place but you
did say that the surface of last
scattering
would not
go over the horizon it would just get
weaker and weaker
so the galaxies other than our local
cluster are going to move through the
surface
yeah except that we won't be able to see
them as galaxies at that point
we'll just see them merge into the uh
they'll get so red-shifted that they'll
get red-shifted down to the same three
degrees and it'll be hard to distinguish
them from any of the other blacks so the
service of last scattering depends on
where you are because the astronomers
and those galaxies are not going to see
themselves moving through the surface of
last scatter oh they're not going to see
no no they're going to see us moving
through the surface of last scattering
right
right everybody's on an equal footing
i seen maybe a ronnie standing call that
you know the first
the size of the universe is some orders
of magnitude larger than what we can see
now yeah is that evident from what you
said not yet
not yet
it becomes evident
when we talk about
measurements of the geometry of space
and we can measure the geometry of space
basically measure the sums of angles of
triangles but how big a triangle very
very big triangles
what we can do
here we are at the center
we look out and we see the surface of
less scattering way out here
and we see some blob in the surface of
last scattering
what is it it's a blob of over density
or under density or whatever it happens
to be
some kind of the surface of last
scattering is somewhat blobby
it's got some
lumpiness in it we see a lump and we
have very good reason to believe that
that lump has a certain size okay
we draw a triangle
we also know with fairly good precision
by now
the distance
to the surface of last scattering so we
draw a triangle
an isosceles triangle with two d's
and let's call it uh the third leg call
it l for length or l for lump
okay
now if we have a triangle like this and
we know d is an and and l
we know this angle
theta
we know the angle if space is flat
if space is positively curved
then this angle would be bigger than we
would estimate from euclidean geometry
if space is negatively curved this is
going to be the subject of next week
negative and positive curvature but
depending on the curvature of space
we would either see this angle bigger or
less bigger or smaller or equal to uh
to what we would expect
for the euclidean geometry
what do we find
we find that to about two percent or
better or one percent or better or
better that euclidean geometry is
correct that means that space is flat
it is very much like measuring triangles
for me standing at the center
looking out some distance a thousand
feet or 100 feet or whatever it is
some object of known size out there and
looking at the angle
and discovering
that the angle is consistent with
euclidean geometry i know the size i see
some battleship out on the horizon
no no not quite on the horizon any
closer i know that battleship is how big
is a battleship how many how many feet
how many
800 feet i know that that's the
battleship missouri was missouri a
battleship
the bismarck i see the bismarck out
there
right
i see the bismarck the bismarck is
bigger than 800 feet i bet
and i know just how big it is i also
have reason to think i know exactly how
far it is and i measure the angle
and i see that it satisfies euclidean
geometry
with a flat
earth
well not quite flat i don't know that
it's exactly flat
but i know it's flat to a good
approximation
that tells me
that the earth is bigger significantly
bigger than the distance to the bismarck
yeah yeah yeah
this this is good for battleships but
what's an example of an object out there
that we know the size of
we'll come to that oh
next week
lumps the largest lumps in the microwave
background
and we think we know their size because
we know how long it took them to evolve
and we know the speed of sound and so a
variety of things
uh
but it's it's the largest lumps that are
seen on the uh on the microwave
background
it would also turn out that romantic is
not
experimentally it's very close to a
constant
when
you
incidentally
when you read about it if you read about
it and you read about the measurement of
w
if people tell you that they've measured
w to be minus one to good accuracy
that's the same thing as saying that the
vacuum energy is constant
so
if you read the scientific american that
astronomers have concluded that the
strange parameter that they call w
is minus 1 and it's getting more and
more and more closer to one
that that's an indication that the
vacuum energy is constant
and uh how close is it
it's uh something like one plus or minus
uh
well it can only go on one side but to
within about ten or five percent that's
one
minus one
would general relativity work with a uh
a vacuum energy that
in which the equation statement
there are ways of making a dropping
hospital yeah so so that is
so at least in principle so general
relativity doesn't exclude the
possibility of
of more radical
the vacuum energy is something which
[Music]
is um
good reason to believe is there the
other things there's much less reason to
believe
there's no singularity or anything at w
equals zero is there things are things
are well no there's nothing w equals
zero is just non-relativistic cold
matter
w equals zero
w equals one not minus one it's believed
there's good reasons
uh
to believe that w has to lie between
minus one and one
w being minus two would really violate
general relativity w equaling plus two
will also buy
so the required special relativity
so the density
calculation for matter and for radiation
you you assume that the energy was
constant and then you adjusted the scale
factor to figure out the formula
the numbers constant we use that the
change in energy is pv
so we assumed
that if we had an imaginary box that was
following a unit volume
and
the
universe expanded
that the uh the imaginary box moving
along with it that work would be done on
the walls by the expansion and that
would account exactly for the change in
energy
okay now this can be done using fancier
there are fancier ways to do this but uh
yeah but that doesn't assume the total
energy was fixed right and so the larger
volume means a lower energy density okay
yeah that's right the total energy
total energy is fixed so that's true for
the first two but for the vacuum energy
the density is constant so that implies
the energy this equation is satisfied
that's energy that is energy
conservation
all right well come on remind me remind
me to talk about energy conservation
the trouble with energy conservation is
that the energy of the universe is zero
so it doesn't say very much
[Music]
you